Finding Aid for the Orville Harry Brown Papers Biomed.0188
UCLA Library Special Collections
Orville Harry Brown papers
1886-1940
UCLA Library Special Collections
Brown, Orville Harry
Biomed.0188
0.5 Linear Feet (1 document box)
Orville Harry Brown was born in Kansas July 18, 1875 and died in So. California on July 25, 1943. In 1905 he received both a Ph.D. from the University of Chicago and an M.D. from St. Louis University. At various times Dr. Brown taught at the university level, served as Physician-in-Chief and then Superintendent of the Missouri State Sanatorium for the Treatment of Pulmonary Tuberculosis, and as Arizona State Superintendent of Public Health and Secretary of the State Board of Health. He was the editor of "Southwestern Medicine" for many years, and authored two books. These papers deal exclusively with Dr. Brown's professional life, consisting mainly of reprints and a few formal reports. They also contain many (crumbling) newspaper clippings on the Spanish American War, President McKinley, and considerable material on the Committee of One Hundred for National Health (an offshoot of the American Association for the Advancement of Science) and the Committee's supporting group, the American Health League.
Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9957872523606533
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Los Angeles Country Medical Association (LACMA) to the UCLA Biomedical Library.
Biography
Orville Harry Brown was born in Sabetha, Kansas, on July 18, 1875 and died in Arcadia, California on July 25, 1943. He attended Ottawa (KS) University, received an AB degree from the University of Kansas in 1901, and in 1905 a Ph.D. from the University of Chicago and the M.D. degree from St. Louis University. He did graduate work at the Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole during two summers, and post-graduate studies in Vienna and London during 1906.
At various times Dr. Brown taught physiology, pharmacology, and medicine at the University of Kansas, the University of Chicago, and St. Louis University. From 1907 to 1909 Dr. Brown served as Physician-in-Chief and then Superintendent of the Missouri State Sanatorium for the Treatment of Pulmonary Tuberculosis, Mount Vernon, MO. In 1918 he was State Superintendent of Public Health in Arizona, and Secretary of its State Board of Health. For many years Dr. Brown was the editor of "Southwestern Medicine". In addition to numerous articles he wrote two books, "Laboratory Physiology" (1905), and "Asthma" (1916).
Dr. Brown was a Fellow of the American Medical Association, the American College of Physicians, and the Royal Society of Medicine, London, and he held memberships in the American College of Chest Physicians and the American Association of Biological Chemists. He was certified by the American Board of Internal Medicine. He was married, and had one daughter.
Scope and Content
The papers deal exclusively with Dr. Brown's professional life, but cover that in only very partial fashion. There are reprints of articles and a very few of the administrative reports he submitted to Missouri and Arizona institutions. There is nothing about his academic life nor, apart from published case reports, about his activities as a clinical physician. There is no correspondence or other documentation of his interactions with colleagues.
The mass of newspaper clippings reveal Dr. Brown's interest in the Spanish American War, especially focused on the policies of President McKinley. There is also considerable material dealing with the Committee of One Hundred for National Health, an offshoot of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and the Committee's supporting group, the American Health League. It is not clear what relationship Dr. Brown held with these groups, but he was possibly a member of the American Health League and was interested in its goals.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Writings by OHB, 1904-1940. 3 folders
Series 2. Miscellaneous Materials, 1886-1908. 16 folders
Physicians -- United States -- Archival resources.; American Health League; Brown, Orville Harry; American Association for the Advancement of Science. Committee of One Hundred on National Health
- Writings by OHB, 1904-1940; Series 1.; 3 folders
  Scope and Contents note
  journal reprints and cut pages, reports, pamphlets
  - Journal reprints and cut pages., 1904-1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    18 items from "American Journal of Physiology", "Journal of the American Medical Association", and other physiological and clinical titles
  - Journal reprints and cut pages., 1908-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    47 items from various clinical titles, especially, in the later years, from "Southwestern Medicine"
  - Pamphlets., 1909-1918 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    1) "Missouri State Sanatorium: Some information for persons desiring admission to the Missouri State Sanatorium for the treatment of pulmonary tuberculosis, by Dr. O.H. Brown, Physician-in-Chief. Mount Vernon, Missouri"; 2) "The Missouri State Sanatorium (first biennial report). Mount Vernon, MO, Jan. 1909"; 3) Bulletin of the Arizona State Board of Health", 6(8), Oct. 1918; 4) "Some facts about the climate of Phoenix and the Salt River Valley of Arizona; a collection of papers ... read before the Maricopa County Medical Society...."
- Miscellaneous Materials, 1886-1908; Series 2.; 16 folders
  This series contains materials by and about the Committee of One Hundred on National Health and the American Health League, newspaper clippings from the 1880s and 1890, and various other clippings and reprints.
  - Journal reprint., 1906 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "The economic advisability of inaugurating a national organization of health," by J. Pease Norton, "Journal of the American Medical Association", Sep. 29, 1906; read before the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Ithaca, N.Y., June 30, 1906
  - Publications of the Committee of One Hundred on National Health, organized under the auspices of the American Association for the Advancement of Science and The American Health League, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    publication nos. 10-16, 18-20, and five other pamphlets
    General note
    for publication no. 16, see [Box 1: 6]
  - "To the grewsome [sic] record of convictions set forth in this pamphlet your attention is respectfully invited". (Box 1, Folder 6)
    published by the Public Health Defense League, N.Y.
  - Pages and articles from "The Literary Digest"., 1891-1900 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    subjects covered: human physiology, exercise, sleep; science and invention; eminent men; miscellany
  - Articles about Charles Dickens. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1) "The homes and haunts of Dickens," by Anna Leach, in "Munsey's Magazine", pp. 240-250, no date or volume no.; 2) two pages (13-14) of "In the footsteps of Dickens," no identification
  - Pages from medical journals., 1891-1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1) "Proceedings of Societies" in "New York Medical Journal", Sep. 26, 1891: 353-354; 2) "Six-day bicycle races" in "The Medical News", Dec. 18, 1897: 801-802
  - Pages from Harper's Weekly., 1886-1898 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Two unidentified columns. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    1) "The dog in India," reprinted from "Revue Scientifique", Paris, June 11, 1892; 2) "Is it a crime to be rich?" (no identification)
  - "The cost of war," by George B. Waldron. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    p. 169-171, no other identification
  - Newspaper clippings., 1880s (Box 1, Folder 13)
    from: "New York Herald" and its "Sunday Supplement", "Brooklyn Sunday Press", and "New York World"
  - Newspaper clippings., 1890s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    from: "The Morning Press", Santa Barbara, Calif.; "New York Herald" and its "Sunday Supplement"; "Harper's Weekly"; "The Daily Telegraph", [London]; "The Argonaut", San Francisco
  - Newspaper clippings., 1900s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    from Pueblo [Colorado?]
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Some old visiting-cards". (Box 1, Folder 17)
    from: "The Strand Magazine", p. 401-406 (no date or volume)
  - Poem, "Morituri salutamus," by Henry W. Longfellow. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    from: "Harper's Magazine", p. 442-[446], no date or volume
    poem for the fiftieth anniversary of the Class of 1825 of Bowdoin College
  - Poem, "Grey kitty's fortune," by L. W. K. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    no other identification; handwritten copy